<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-01-13T15:10:36+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Kyle Macleod</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">Treasury growth targets are doomed to fail</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2022/09/23/welcome-to-jekyll.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Treasury growth targets are doomed to fail" /><published>2022-09-23T20:25:51+01:00</published><updated>2022-09-23T20:25:51+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2022/09/23/welcome-to-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2022/09/23/welcome-to-jekyll.html"><![CDATA[<p>Kwasi Kwarteng’s ‘mini-budget’ announced this morning comes in the wake of the ambitious decision to redirect the treasury to focus entirely on achieving an annual economic growth rate of 2.5 per cent.</p>

<p>This policy is a genuine attempt to spur the UK economy and restore growth rates to those seen prior to the 2008 financial crises. However, it’s difficult to expect to bring up UK growth rates at anywhere near the rate which the government has aimed for.</p>

<p>When these targets are inevitably missed due to financial conditions largely outside of the government’s control, the Chancellor of the Exchequer will have handed his opponents a stick to beat him with.</p>

<p>Truss and Kwarteng have frequently criticised the Treasury for both its lack of ambition surrounding economic growth, and its short-term focus. They have also both previously stated their belief that when trying to eradicate poverty and achieve greater prosperity, creating economic growth is of a higher importance than the redistribution of existing wealth.</p>

<p>It is therefore not surprising that the new government has proposed massive overhauls to the treasury’s operations. This strategy also comes at a time when many other government operations have struggled due to a lack of transparency surrounding their ultimate purpose or remit. The treasury is fundamentally different from other organisations such as the Bank of England however, as it does not have one clear goal to aim for. This is required by the nature of the department, as it must use nuance and wide-ranging objectives in its role to best serve the UK economy.</p>

<p>A target of 2.5 per cent, at a time when many experts are predicting low or even negative growth, will lead the government towards fiscally irresponsible policies designed to achieve their goal at any cost. To ensure balance between short and long-term economic ambitions, the Chancellor of the Exchequer should set a more fluid target which considers UK growth rates in the context of global economic conditions. This would provide the budgetary freedom required to enact lasting change without the risk of short-term financial instability.</p>

<p>Setting a static target will also likely cause rifts and a lack of cooperation within the treasury; senior officials will surely expect the next government to discontinue this hard growth target policy as they struggle to manage it with their other ambitions, and civil servants will therefore be reluctant to commit to the changes it requires.</p>

<p>The removal of senior treasury official Tom Scholar from his long-held post will also affect the department’s willingness to cooperate in this regard. Kwasi Kwarteng may therefore face a rebellion among senior civil servants in 1 Horse Guards Road, who will be continually conscious of their other objectives such as reducing the deficit and ensuring fiscal stability.</p>

<p>In the past, governments have experimented with various methods to try to eliminate the confusion existing within the treasury and prioritize economic growth. The most notable example was Harold Wilson’s attempt to create a separate government department with a remit for ensuring growth (named the Department for Economic Affairs).</p>

<p>There are many similarities between the period in which the DEA was formed and our current era, including a large deficit and challenges to the value of sterling. The DEA eventually fell apart as budget restrictions left it with little money to allocate and its functions were reabsorbed back into the treasury. Kwarteng’s growth target will likely fail for similar reasons that the DEA did: as the government struggles to commit to the necessary budget reduction required to give weight to the policy under harsh economic conditions, the treasury will revert to business as usual.</p>

<p>The next report by the Office for Budget Responsibility will likely be scathing as we see the short-term consequences of the Chancellor’s commitment to their 2.5 per cent target in the form of a higher deficit and a rapidly falling value of the pound. The government have therefore created a situation in which the public will need to see strong results from their policy changes in order for them to stand a chance of re-election. Today, the Chancellor has illustrated his commitment to his philosophy on how best to achieve growth, and the results of this approach will either make or break him.</p>

<hr />
<p><em>Originally posted on the blog <a href="https://www.1828.org.uk/author/kyle-macleod/">1828</a>.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Kwasi Kwarteng’s ‘mini-budget’ announced this morning comes in the wake of the ambitious decision to redirect the treasury to focus entirely on achieving an annual economic growth rate of 2.5 per cent.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The SNP must end free tuition fees for Scotland’s future</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2022/08/24/Another.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The SNP must end free tuition fees for Scotland’s future" /><published>2022-08-24T20:25:51+01:00</published><updated>2022-08-24T20:25:51+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2022/08/24/Another</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2022/08/24/Another.html"><![CDATA[<p>Since their introduction in 2008, free tuition fees in Scotland have been the cornerstone of the Scottish National Party’s higher education policy. The justification for this policy is simple and was best summarised by then Education Secretary Fiona Hyslop, who said “We believe access to education should be based on ability to learn, not ability to pay”.</p>

<p>This is an attractive argument: ensuring that university admissions remain meritocratic is of vital importance for both moral and practical reasons. It has, however, become apparent that rather than supporting equality of opportunity in education, the SNP policy in this area has left many of Scotland’s poorest students behind.</p>

<p>All Scottish students studying for their first undergraduate degree in Scotland pay zero tuition fees. This has been a longstanding policy designed to bridge the attainment gap between students of various incomes. The method for funding this policy is two-fold: the Scottish government pays a fee of £1,250 each academic year for each pupil studying at a university while simultaneously placing caps on the number of domestic students that a university can admit. Universities are subject to hefty fines if they admit more domestic students than their government-enforced cap allows.</p>

<p>The fee provided to Scottish universities for each Scottish student pales in comparison to the £9,250 per student that a university can charge a student from elsewhere in the UK, and it certainly falls far short of the typical fees paid by international students.</p>

<p>This has led to perverse incentives for Scottish universities: there are huge financial gains to be made by prioritising non-domestic students for admissions and this is exactly what we have seen. SNP policy in this area has created a system where the lowest-income students in Scotland are less likely than their English counterparts to be able to attend university; the benefits from the policy being accrued by higher-income students who would have attended university regardless.</p>

<p>These low-income students are particularly excluded from Scotland’s four elite ancient universities (St. Andrews, Edinburgh, Glasgow, Aberdeen) who are able to attract large numbers of students from outside of Scotland. In 2021, the universities of St. Andrews and Edinburgh earned a mere 15 and 18 per cent of their respective total income from the Scottish Funding Council which reimburses universities for admitting Scottish students. It is therefore not surprising that they have been forced to focus on generating income elsewhere.</p>

<p>Scotland’s universities are in a state of disarray; the universities with the reputation required to attract non-domiciled students have maintained funding levels for teaching and research by admitting fewer Scottish students, while the universities without this option have suffered from large financial deficits. In both cases, Scottish students have suffered from lower quality teaching and fewer places than their counterparts in the rest of the UK.</p>

<p>The solution to this problem is simple: end the disastrous policy regime by aligning university fees with the rest of the UK’s universities. This would not only create more opportunities for Scottish students, who would be more likely to consider studying elsewhere in the UK, but would also increase the number of domestic students Scottish universities could admit. This would however be a drastically unpopular decision: the students already admitted to Scottish universities have high incentives to maintain the current system at the expense of their peers.</p>

<p>Encouraging Scottish students to study in the rest of the UK would also be counterproductive to the SNP’s aims of isolating Scottish students from the rest of the UK in order to increase the nationalist sentiment that is required for their future independence referendum to succeed. It is, however, vital to prevent the future decay of Scotland’s great universities.</p>

<p>In order to give Scottish students of all income backgrounds the greatest range of choices for their future, the Scottish government must end the no tuition fees policy and allow their universities to compete with other UK universities. It is only with this change that we can close the educational attainment gap that has been generated as a result of this disastrous policy and generate the funding required to educate Scotland’s students.</p>

<hr />
<p><em>Originally posted on the blog <a href="https://www.1828.org.uk/author/kyle-macleod/">1828</a>.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Since their introduction in 2008, free tuition fees in Scotland have been the cornerstone of the Scottish National Party’s higher education policy. The justification for this policy is simple and was best summarised by then Education Secretary Fiona Hyslop, who said “We believe access to education should be based on ability to learn, not ability to pay”.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Gearing Up For the Ride of Our Lives</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2021/11/19/Electric-Vehicles.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gearing Up For the Ride of Our Lives" /><published>2021-11-19T19:25:51+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-19T19:25:51+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2021/11/19/Electric%20Vehicles</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2021/11/19/Electric-Vehicles.html"><![CDATA[<p>Chronic UK fuel shortages made headlines last year. The disruption caused by the pandemic and Brexit, in tandem with opportunistic media coverage, led to large-scale panic buying of fuel. A consequent shortfall of fuel and public pressure forced the UK government to take action, going as far as enlisting the army to transport fuel across the nation. But we are not out of the woods yet. The economy is still under pressure: businesses are facing astronomical shipping prices and lower consumer discretionary spending. Amid this chaos, however, are encouraging signs.</p>

<p>Tired of waiting in hour-long queues to get their hands on less than a week’s worth of fuel, drivers’ interest has started to shift away from gas-guzzlers towards electric alternatives. Electric vehicle (EV) sales in October 2021 were almost 50% higher than at the same time last year; this statistic becomes even more remarkable given that total car sales decreased by a third in the same period. What’s more, 15% of car sales in the UK now involve electric vehicles.</p>

<p>It seems that the fuel crisis provided the encouragement many needed to make a definitive switch to EVs.</p>

<h2 id="turned-off">Turned Off?</h2>

<p>Despite the current data offering a source of cautious optimism, there is good reason to be sceptical about the pace of EV adoption in the UK. For one, a global semiconductor shortage that has affected manufacturers of low-cost cars has hampered sales of conventional cars worldwide. The scarcity is unlikely to last, however, as the US is now subsidising the manufacture of semiconductors.</p>

<p>Fuel prices are volatile, so it would be unwise to rely on a persistent rise in fuel prices to drive EV adoption—at least in the short term. That said, if fuel prices continue to fluctuate sharply, risk-averse consumers may be willing to pay a premium to rely on relatively stable electricity prices instead.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Tired of waiting in hour-long queues to get their hands on less than a week’s worth of fuel, drivers’ interest has started to shift away from gas-guzzlers towards electric alternatives.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Unsurprisingly, consumers consider more than just operational costs when choosing their next car: limited driving range, long charging times and high initial prices of current EV models may deter consumers from making the switch to electric.</p>

<p>These are issues that manufacturers are working to overcome, but they remain burdensome for EV owners in the short term. It is also worth considering the high costs manufacturers face in transitioning from the production of conventional fuel vehicles to the production of electric vehicles. It may be unrealistic to expect that the motor industry has the impetus to transition to a greener pattern of production and consumption. Instead, a serious effort to transform the sector may demand government policy.</p>

<h2 id="rage-against-the-machine">Rage Against the Machine</h2>

<p>The benefits of the widespread adoption of green vehicles are evident. Not only would the climate benefit from a reduction in greenhouse gas emissions, but societies would also benefit through reduced emissions of harmful pollutants (e.g., noise pollution in major cities), the stabilisation of the electricity grid, and reduced dependence on imported oil.</p>

<p>These benefits combined may justify government intervention that steers consumers towards electric vehicles. One such intervention may be reducing the effective price differential between EVs and petrol vehicles—perhaps through direct subsidies or increased taxation on high-emission vehicles.</p>

<p>Alternatively, making EVs more convenient for drivers by increasing the number of available ultra-fast charging ports may spur purchases. Elsewhere, governments have promoted the adoption of EVs through similar policies; for instance, the introduction of road toll exemptions in Norway and free parking for EV owners. Future commitment to EVs may include designated lanes on motorways.</p>

<p>There are several options for policymakers to promote electrification in the motor industry. Yet, perhaps the most effective policies will be those that make the benefits of EV ownership visible and enviable to all. Innovation will make the green revolution in road transport inevitable.</p>

<p>Effective policies are needed to accelerate the adoption of EVs and decelerate rising emissions. Can governments flip the switch in time?</p>

<hr />
<p><em>Originally published in <a href="https://issuu.com/insightedinburgh/docs/final_insight_2021_autumn_147_copies">Insight</a> - Autumn 2021</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Chronic UK fuel shortages made headlines last year. The disruption caused by the pandemic and Brexit, in tandem with opportunistic media coverage, led to large-scale panic buying of fuel. A consequent shortfall of fuel and public pressure forced the UK government to take action, going as far as enlisting the army to transport fuel across the nation. But we are not out of the woods yet. The economy is still under pressure: businesses are facing astronomical shipping prices and lower consumer discretionary spending. Amid this chaos, however, are encouraging signs.]]></summary></entry></feed>